If you had caught me straight out of college
لو التقيتني بعد خروجي من الكلية
in the halls of the Vermont State House
في ممرات "فيرمونت ستيت هاوس"
where I was a lobbyist in training
حيث كنت مدرب على جماعات الضغط
and asked me what I was going to do with my life,
وسألتني مالذي سوف اقوم به في حياتي
I would have told you
لأجبتك
that I'd just passed the Hanyu Shuiping Kaoshi,
انني اجتزت للتو امتحان " هانيو شويبينج كاوشي"
the Chinese equivalency exam,
امتحان المعادلة الصيني
and I was going to go study law in Beijing,
وكنت سوف اقوم بدراسة القانون في بكين
and I was going to improve U.S.-China relations
وانني سوف اقوم بتقوية العلاقات الامريكية الصينية
through top-down policy changes
خلال التغيرات السياسية من الاعلى للاسفل
and judicial system reforms.
وإصلاح النظام القضائي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I had a plan,
كان لدي خطة,
and I never ever thought
ولم اعتقد ابداً
it would have anything to do
انها سوف تغير اي شيء
with the banjo.
بخصوص الة البانجو
Little did I know
كنت اعرف القليل
what a huge impact it would have on me one night
في احد الليالي كان هناك تأثير كبير علي
when I was at a party
عندما كنت في حفلة
and I heard a sound coming out of a record player
وسمعت صوتاً قادماً من مشغل التسجيلات
in the corner of a room.
في ركن الغرفة
And it was Doc Watson
وكان "دوك واتسون"
singing and playing "Shady Grove."
يغني ويعزف "شادي جروف"
♫ Shady Grove, my little love ♫
♫ شادي جروف يا حبي الصغير ♫
♫ Shady Grove, my darlin' ♫
♫ شادي جروف ,يا حبيبي ♫
♫ Going back to Harlan ♫
♫ سأعود الى هارلان ♫
That sound was just so beautiful,
كان الصوت رائعاً
the sound of Doc's voice
صوت "دوك"
and the rippling groove of the banjo.
وأمواج الة البانجو
And after being totally and completely obsessed
وبعد ان كنت مهووسة تماما
with the mammoth richness and history
بالتاريخ العظيم والضخم
of Chinese culture,
الخاص بالحضارة الصينية,
it was like this total relief
كان تماماً يشبه الانقاذ
to hear something so truly American
ان تسمع شيئاً امريكيا خالصاً
and so truly awesome.
ورائع حقاً
I knew I had to take a banjo with me to China.
علمت انه يجب ان اخذ الة البانجو معي الى الصين
So before going to law school in China
اذاً قبل ان التحق بكلية القانون في الصين
I bought a banjo, I threw it in my little red truck
اشتريت الة البانجو, ووضعته في
and I traveled down through Appalachia
وانتقلت عبر "ابالاشيا"
and I learned a bunch of old American songs,
وتعلمت بضعة اغاني امريكية,
and I ended up in Kentucky
وانتهيت في ولاية كينتاكي
at the International Bluegrass Music Association Convention.
في جمعية موسيقى بلوجراس العالمية
And I was sitting in a hallway one night
وكنت اجلس في المدخل في احد الليالي
and a couple girls came up to me.
وجاءني مجموعة من الفتيات
And they said, "Hey, do you want to jam?"
وقالو "مرحبا ,هل ترغب في العزف الجماعي
And I was like, "Sure."
وأجبت " بالتأكيد"
So I picked up my banjo
فالتقطت الة البانجو
and I nervously played four songs that I actually knew with them.
وبدات اعزف معهن بتوتر اربع اغنيات من التي اعرفها
And a record executive walked up to me
واتجه نحوي مدير تنفيذي لشركة تسجيلات
and invited me to Nashville, Tennessee to make a record.
ودعاني الى " ناشفيل ,تينيسي: " لعمل تسجيل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's been eight years,
كان ذلك منذ ثمانية اعوام,
and I can tell you that I didn't go to China to become a lawyer.
واستطيع اخباركم انني لم اذهب الى الصين لاصبح محامياً
In fact, I went to Nashville.
في الواقع ذهبت الى "ناشفيل"
And after a few months I was writing songs.
وبعد عدة اشهر اصبحت اكتب الاغاني.
And the first song I wrote was in English,
وأول اغنية كتبتها كانت بالانجليزية,
and the second one was in Chinese.
والثانية كانت بالصينية.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
[Chinese]
[باللغة الصينية]
Outside your door the world is waiting.
كنت انتظر خارج بابك.
Inside your heart a voice is calling.
صوت ينادي داخل قلبك.
The four corners of the world are watching,
كانت تنظر اركان العالم الاربعة
so travel daughter, travel.
ارحلي يا ابنتي ,ارحلي.
Go get it, girl.
اذهبي واجلبيه
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's really been eight years since that fated night in Kentucky.
ثمانية اعوام منذ تلك الليلة المحتومة في كنتاكي
And I've played thousands of shows.
وعزفت في الاف العروض
And I've collaborated
وتعاونت
with so many incredible, inspirational musicians around the world.
مع الكثير من الموسيقيين العظام والملهمين في العالم.
And I see the power of music.
ورأيت قوة الموسيقى
to connect cultures.
في ربط الحضارات.
I see it when I stand on a stage
رايت ذلك عنما كنت على المسرح
in a bluegrass festival in east Virginia
في احتفالية فن البلوجراس في شرق فيرجينيا
and I look out at the sea of lawn chairs
ونظرت الى مشهد الكراسي
and I bust out into a song in Chinese.
وانتقلت الى اغنية صينية
[Chinese]
[باللغة الصينية]
And everybody's eyes just pop wide open
واتسعت اعين الحضور
like it's going to fall out of their heads.
كما لو كانت سوف تخرج من رؤوسهم
And they're like, "What's that girl doing?"
وكان لسان حالها مالذي تفعله تلك الفتاة
And then they come up to me after the show
وجاءوا الي بعد العرض
and they all have a story.
وكان لكل منهم قصة
They all come up and they're like,
جاءوا وخبروني قصصهم وكانت تشبه
"You know, my aunt's sister's babysitter's dog's chicken went to China
"هل تعلمين ان دجاجة كلب جليسة بنت خالتي ذهبت الى الصين
and adopted a girl."
وتبنت فتاة"
And I tell you what, it like everybody's got a story.
وكما قلت لكم لكل منهم قصة
It's just incredible.
كان شيئا لا يصدق
And then I go to China
وبعد ذلك ذهبت الى الصين
and I stand on a stage at a university
ووقفت في مسرح الجامعة
and I bust out into a song in Chinese
وبدأت اغني بالصينية
and everybody sings along
وغنى الجميع معي
and they roar with delight
وهتفو في فرحة
at this girl
لهذه الفتاة
with the hair and the instrument,
ذات الشعر والالة
and she's singing their music.
وتغني موسيقاهم
And I see, even more importantly,
ولاحظت اهمية
the power of music to connect hearts.
قوة الموسيقى لربط القلوب
Like the time I was in Sichuan Province
مثلاً عندما كنت في مقاطعة سيشوان
and I was singing for kids in relocation schools
وكنت اغني للأطفال في المدارس
in the earthquake disaster zone.
في منطقة كارثة الزلزال
And this little girl comes up to me.
وجاءت الي تلك الفتاة الصغيرة
[Chinese]
[بالصينية]
"Big sister Wong,"
"اختي الكبيرة ونج"
Washburn, Wong, same difference.
واشبورن,وونج, نفس الاختلاف
"Big sister Wong, can I sing you a song
"اختي الكبيرة وونج,هل يمكنني ان اغني لك الأغنية
that my mom sang for me
التي غنتها لي والدتي
before she was swallowed in the earthquake?"
قبل ان تختفي في الزلزال؟"
And I sat down,
فجلست
she sat on my lap.
وجلست في حضني
She started singing her song.
وبدأت تغني اغنيتها
And the warmth of her body
ودفء جسمها
and the tears rolling down her rosy cheeks,
والدموع التي انهمرت على خدودها.
and I started to cry.
وبدأت في البكاء
And the light that shone off of her eyes
والنور الذي شع من عيونها
was a place I could have stayed forever.
كان ذلك المكان الذي ارغب في البقاء فيه الى الابد
And in that moment, we weren't our American selves,
في تلك اللحظة لم نكن نتصرف كامريكيين
we weren't our Chinese selves,
ولا كصينيين
we were just mortals
كنا بشراً فقط
sitting together in that light that keeps us here.
نجلس معاً في الضوء الذي جمعنا معاً
I want to dwell in that light
اردت ان اسكن في ذلك الضوء
with you and with everyone.
معكم ومع الجميع
And I know U.S.-China relations
وأعرف العلاقات الصينية الامريكية
doesn't need another lawyer.
لا تحتاج محامياً اخر
Thank you.
شكراً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)